all right this is the first video in the
Sicilian series and I guess by nature is
gonna be a little bit broader than is
appropriate for this particular kind of
venue I have to prime pad at least a
little bit of context is what I'm
talking about
hopefully in the future we'll actually
be able to go back and recreate this
particular video to be more I guess
specific so context the notion of the
city and project is based upon a I guess
a premise and a possibility so the
premise is that the the city is
foundational to the nature of what I've
called game a or to the the fundamental
basis of the toolkit that gives rise to
the kinds of civilizations the human
beings of this far been able to create
so I'm making a proposition that city is
more fundamental than civilization the
possibility that I am proposing is that
we are now within a threshold we are now
near to a point we can in fact innovate
a new way living together that is
different as a different basis than the
city and there for and thereby that
transition is fundamental it moves us
from one basis that gives rise to entire
architecture of civilizations to
potentially a very different one which
if we wanted to use that language we
could say game Bay although I suppose
ambivalent about that these days so
nobody get into the into the depth of
this particular piece this piece is
about about the first proposition and
some of the context around that and to
do that I have to go into a little bit
of depth so this video is probably gonna
be on the order of like 10 or 12 minutes
I apologize for the length the the core
theory here comes from work that was
done largely around the Santa Fe
Institute largely with people like
Geoffrey West and we spent court and
many others and you can read about it
actually in the book called scale the
differed West produced the past couple
of years and I'll just give the a brief
summary kind of compress the piece that
I think is most relevant what they were
looking at was particular
characteristics that are called
scaling loss which is to say if I if I
increase some particular characteristic
like let's say for example I have a one
brick and that brick weighs one pound
and I increase one characteristic so I
increase from one brick to ten bricks so
this gives an increasing number how many
pounds do I have well in the case of
bricks it's a linear scaling loss if I
have gone from one brick to ten bricks
I've gone from one pound to ten pound
and they were looking at various all
kinds of different systems in nature
looking at what kinds of scaling laws
were there what they found was that
there was a very profound fundamental
that in many important characteristics
like for example the ratio between body
mass and metabolism or body mass and
like the amount of vascular tissue like
how long was your vascular system if you
kind of could lay it all out and measure
it that there was a an extraordinary
regularity of what are called sub linear
scaling laws and very specifically in
fact 25 which is to say for example if I
have a mouse that weighs 100 grams and I
and it has the same metabolic rate X and
I double its mass to 200 grams I don't
in fact double it its metabolism in fact
right you're still going because my 100%
and increase it by only eighty-five
percent more or less like I'm just
trying to brush broad brush into the
zone here and this the sub linear
scaling is very fundamentally
characteristic you might even see it's
at the very heart of living systems
specifically dissipative systems I think
but in any event living systems so with
you looking at cells or organisms we're
looking at mammals or reptiles whether
you're looking at by the way trees or
forests right entire ecosystems that are
multi species you still see these seen
this exact same kind of sub linear
scaling dynamic and that's huge is it's
an enormous ly important finding and it
talks about for example how systems have
limits to growth built in elephants are
kind of as big as they're gonna get
blue wheels are as big as they're gonna
get in the context of that particular
niche for example and when they wouldn't
start looking at human systems they
found the human systems also more or
less and we give you the exception a
minute
fell under the same rule
so if I take a corporation and I add
more people I don't for example increase
revenue per person linearly actually
increases I'm kind of like a asymptotes
so when I go from a thousand people to
two thousand people I don't double the
revenue per person in fact I attend to
actually each per capita input reduces
which means that corporations have a
natural asymptote at a certain point
you're just not getting any more
productivity out of the individuals that
you're adding into the system we also
seen for example cities that if you take
a look at the population of a city and
you look at for example the length of
roads in the city or the sort of length
total measure of say telephone lines or
ours or sewers the same basic
characteristic if I double the
population of a city the the amount of
the length of roads does not double it
increases by eighty five percent okay
that's cool so what's that saying is
these human built systems are very much
like biological systems so a city is
like in in this context a city is like a
forest but and this but is the point of
this video frankly the plenty entire
series to be perfectly frank with regard
to other characteristics cities and only
in cities did they find not just not a
sub linear scaling metric but a super
linear scaling metric so what that means
what it meant was that with regard to
something like say income per capita so
I've got a city of a million everybody
makes let's just say on average ten
thousand dollars a month if I double the
population of the city the per capita
income goes up by about fifteen percent
so it's 115 so instead of everybody
making $10,000 a month now everybody
makes eleven thousand five hundred now
this is a very important thing because
it means that if I'm choosing between
city a and city B and City a is a five
hundred thousand person city and city P
is a million person city then on average
just me being exactly the same nothing
about me I will make more money going to
city be about 15% more hardly enough and
by the way if there's a city see it's a
two million person city on average I'll
make more money going to cities see now
of course what that means is that more
likely I will choose the biggest city
which means the biggest cities gonna
tend to get bigger and here it is the
very powerful thing in some very strong
sense cities are to people like stars
are to atoms there's a desire sometimes
a gravitational tractor to pack as many
people as possible into the city cuz do
you increase the population then you
increase things like wealth and by the
way also innovation so this gives rise
to a very powerful dynamic just like a
star by the way where a star kind of
wants to collapse to a singularity from
the point of view of gravity and then
it's pushing against the electro Matic
magnetic force that prevents the atoms
from getting any closer together they
can and that gives you the dynamic of a
star cities have the attractor of
wanting to get more people in the city
to increase the wealth and innovation
and other variables and it's facing the
repulsor of for example constraints
around but for one thing people have
physical bodies so they have to be in
space it is only until you can pack into
a particular piece of space or giving
them food but there's only so much food
you can produce in the city if you're
producing the food out of the city
you've got transportation so if you can
only walk for example then this one's so
far you can bring food and water etc and
also moving waste out of the city as
constraints and so we see is a kind of a
seeking on the part of cities to
maximally use the technology that is
available to them to overcome the
limitations or the constraints of
physical bodies to pack as many human
beings as possible into cities to
thereby get this super linear growth in
wealth and innovation and other
characteristics and then effectively
running into the limits of that so the
Romans could build aqueducts but the
Babylonians couldn't don't knock it off
so yeah limit when we invented the a the
elevators something could go up past
three or four floors where people could
we walk on stairs and something build
skyscrapers and talk a lot more people
into the same space and okay next piece
this piece is by the way substantially
more let's call it theoretical I'm
extending this out you creates fragility
so the city is endeavouring to spring as
many people into it notice that as it
brings more people and it gets more
wealth and it gets more innovation so it
has the capacity to start trying to
figure out how to solve problems so
again there was a point at which room
couldn't bring enough water in but they
can figure out how to build aqueducts
they build these aqueducts and pull
water from hundreds of miles away to be
able to continue to support the
population now here's a proposition the
proposition is effectively the entire
population of a region is composed of
the city and its support infrastructure
and so the hypothesis is that the city
is trying to get as many people as
possible into the center and literally
everything that isn't in the center is
just support infrastructure so if you
look at the contemporary Western world
in particular you see something that
looks like that you've got giant cities
that have sort of evaporated the
population out of it out of their local
environment created sort of population
deserts except for the location that can
provide support infrastructure and in
some cases that support infrastructure
has to do with locations where people
who really don't want to be in cities
can still be okay and then what happens
is is that the dynamic of packing more
and more people and pushes it to the
limits which means that is optimizing
for the capacity to increase the number
of people in the city which means that
it's becoming fragile logistics it's as
intense as it can food distribution gets
his intense as it can water distribution
gets tensed as it can you're also
running into situations where by the way
things like crime and disease also tend
to increase super linearly so you have
to build techniques to try to reduce
that visa fee innovation innovation
welfare fighting against crime and
disease and so minor perturbation as the
system becomes more and more optimized
for maximizing population in your
particular constraints of technology
boom you gotta collapse and then that
collapse creates a collapse of the
entire civilization so by hypothesis for
example I would propose that the
collapse of the Roman Empire was in some
very distinct sense the actual collapse
of the city of Rome and everything else
was support infrastructure now that's a
pretty bold claim and I don't
necessarily need to hang my hat too much
on that last piece but the key idea here
is city attraction repulsion dynamic as
being fundamental to the nature of
civilization until now because if you
think about it if you look at it deeply
what you might say what I'm proposing is
that the core attractor is actually not
the city the dynamic is actually more
abstract and what we've seen in the city
is really just the fact that bodies are
human beings in bed and bodies the thing
that really wants to happen the thing
the real driver of the super linear
scaling metric is Minds in relationship
intelligence distinct intelligences
interacting through some mechanism and
it's because minds are embodied that we
have cities up until very recently the
only way for minds to interact if you
had bring bodies relatively close to
each other and those are subject to the
constraints of effectively travel and
now more recently telecommunications but
telecommunications has been relatively
weak like a telegraph telephone
television these various kinds of media
that created the possibility of
interaction relationship over
non-physical distances have changed
things a lot but they still haven't been
strong enough to overcome the
possibility for relationship that exists
in physical proximity but now it looks
like you may be either at or near the
tipping point where things like this
medium it more importantly things like
video conferences and I strongly suspect
the next wave of virtual reality have
enough possibility of relationship in
the virtual that we can in fact decouple
the attractor and the repulsion so thus
idiom is a concept based on that premise
the CVM is a concept that says
if we can render unto the virtual what
is best done in the virtual and render
into the physical what is best under the
physical and then bring those back into
proper relationship we can change the
whole game that's what I mean what I
mean is creative generative
collaboration in the virtual and now
here we can in fact have a single city
one place for all minds at least in
principle can be in right relationship
with each other they can communicate
they can interrelate no longer
constrained in the same way by
physicality and by the way this also
means that we have to be thinking very
clearly about what are the right ways to
bring those minds into relationship how
do we actually build this virtual
environment so it's maximally generative
there's a whole new space we have to
take this seriously not because it's
going to be not an adjunct to
civilization but a fully symmetric basis
to civilization with the physical side
now by the way this implies that we
should get significant increases in
wealth and innovation if I can take the
biggest cities in the world and increase
them by what about seven or eight
doublings I'm increasing wealth by a lot
so for example if I take the population
of Tokyo and now move that to include
the entire human population the average
income would go up by about three or
five X there's a lot okay so that's one
side on the other side when I have made
this decoupling and now buy it is are
not being squeezed together because the
body is the substrate for relationship
now the bodies can be returned to
humaneness
to a more humane way of living living in
the tomorrow limit you're living among
people who you know well strong link
relationships family community living in
nature making sure that the place that
you're living is built at human scale
very walkable very quiet low toxicity
where you always have relationship with
being in the earth being in nature and
and and by the way I suspect that this
is not just awesome
I know not only does it does it give us
back a whole bunch of values that we've
had to give up in the context of the the
gluttony of the city
I suspect it's actually going to be
obligate to enable the virtual to be as
powerful as it needs to be so for
example imagine most people now are
experiencing the fact that interaction
via the virtual like food say for
example in a zoom conference is
substantially more draining than
interaction in the physical mind if I if
I'm in a room of 12 people I'm having a
conversation with 12 people for me at
least as an introvert it's very draining
but it's training us can say X but if I
have that same length of conversation
with those same 12 people but it's all
in a zoom call it is substantially more
draining let's say 2x it's more like the
pipe X but whatever now imagine if when
you finish that zoom conference instead
of dropping back into your body in the
context that you're in now you dropped
into a context that is extremely
nurturing for human beings you're able
to go sit under a shade tree next to
running water maybe even swim in the
water or we could go out and interact
with people with whom you have very
healthy relationship and do something
together like build a wall or digging
the garden or whatever it happens to be
that if a is very human how much more
grounding that is and returns your
nervous system back to a state of health
so that you can then cycle back into the
virtual and extend that creativity and
then generativity like this movement
between the virtual and the physical not
becomes something that we can really
couple read couple in a right way and
get a lot more out of it and a lot more
out of it that is healthy so that's the
notion all right so the idea here is
that we can take this incredibly
powerful generator of wealth and
innovation that has been captured in the
city which has a whole bunch of
characteristics of forcing us into
situations that are increasingly
inhumane
not healthy for humans and pop that
apart and increase it by a factor of 5
to 7 at the virtual level so yeah
something more generative than the
cities that ever dreamed of being but at
the same time recover and get back all
of the human scale living that we've had
to surrender and return to that sort of
wholesomeness of life the the many of us
I think yearns for an
here we are I where we're in that pivot
point the quarantine has shown us
whether we like it or not that many of
the things that we have had to know what
these have thought we had to do in
interaction you know work environment
learning environments much of that can
be done virtually in fact depending on
how the next several months play out
much of it will continue to have to be
done virtually so we're going to be
having to learn those skills and this
gives rise to an opportunity to extend
into that into the experiment and see mm
okay what does that look like if we make
that fundamental and that's we're doing
gosh 18 minutes pretty long probably
shoot this again in different frame and
see if I can make it shorter but but
those who chose to watch this till the
end I hope it was worth it